Aging -- that's the subject of my
upcoming book, "How Not to Age."
This video will give you just a
taste of the body of evidence
I'll be covering in the book.
Check it out.
"The Best Diet for Healthy Aging"
Based on a study of more
than 400,000 people,
replacing just 3% of calories of
animal protein with plant protein
was associated with a 10%
reduction in overall mortality risk.
That comes out to be
about an extra year of life,
swapping out just 3% of any
animal protein with plant protein.
And egg protein was the worst,
mostly found in the egg whites.
Swapping 3% of calories of
egg protein for plant protein
was associated with more than
a 20% reduction in overall mortality,
worse than red meat.
But it's not just about adding years
to your life, but life to your years.
What about changes in dietary intake
of animal versus vegetable protein
and unhealthy aging?
Healthy aging is defined as
"the process of developing
and maintaining
the functional ability that
enables wellbeing in older age."
No one wants to just be a vegetable,
and you may be able to avoid that
by eating more vegetables.
A higher intake of vegetable
protein was associated with
less accumulation of deficits,
based on functional impairments,
self-reported health and vitality,
mental health and diseases,
and the use of health services.
Swapping in just 1% of vegetable
protein calories for animal protein
led to significantly less
deficit accumulation.
Now you may be thinking, duh,
animal protein and animal fat
travel alongside each
other in the same foods,
so maybe this is all just a
saturated fat effect. But no,
even after accounting for fat,
there still seemed to be something
about the animal versus
plant protein sources,
though it's still not clear if
the beneficial health effects
are because of the avoidance
of deleterious effects associated
with animal foods or the
beneficial effects of plants,
though it may be a bit of both.
A recent review in a
dermatology journal on the role
of a whole-food, plant-based
diet in preventing
and reversing skin aging
emphasized this point.
A whole-food, plant-based diet is not
the same thing as just a vegan diet.
You can have a terribly
unhealthy vegan diet.
As a physician, "vegan" just
tells me what you don't eat,
but you actually have to like
to eat your vegetables, too.
But when you do,
a whole-food, plant-based diet
can aid in the prevention,
and in some cases reversal,
of some of the leading chronic
diseases in the United States
as well as the potential for
younger-looking skin due to
telomere lengthening,
maximizing the antioxidant
potential of our cells,
and also eliminating harmful
carcinogens and aging toxins,
known as gerontotoxins,
from entering our bloodstream.
No wonder the highest life
expectancy of any formally
described population
in the world may be
the Adventist vegetarians
in Loma Linda, California,
one of the five original
"blue zones" in the world.
The average life expectancy of
Adventist vegetarian men and women
is into their 80's, about
6 to 10 years longer
than the general population
in California, with vegetarian,
exercising, nut eating, lower
weight, never smokers living
about 9 to 11 years longer than
those lacking those qualities.
So that's like 10 years of life
up for grabs.
Now, substantial gains in life
expectancy would only be worthwhile
if they were also accompanied by
a longer period of good quality life.
Although overall well-being
has not been measured directly,
vegetarian Adventists have been
recorded taking fewer medications,
and logging fewer overnight hospital
stays and surgical procedures
and x-ray examinations,
and the reduced prevalence of
several chronic diseases alone
would presumably make
life likely more worth living.
The most feared disease
associated with getting older
is likely Alzheimer's disease.
Dementia is one of our fastest
growing epidemics, affecting
1 in 10 individuals older
than 65 years of age
and half of all individuals
older than 85.
Alzheimer's is the main type,
and indeed the most feared.
So when we're talking about
"Plant-Based Diets for Healthy Aging,"
particularly intriguing is emerging
evidence that diet plays
a major role in the prevention
of age-related cognitive decline
and Alzheimer's disease.
It has been shown that a diet
rich in fruits, grains, beans,
vegetables, nuts, and seeds
may cut the risk of Alzheimer's
disease by more than a half.
This is the study
they're talking about,
the so-called MIND diet, which
emphasizes natural plant foods,
including specifically berries,
the healthiest fruits,
and greens,
the healthiest vegetables,
while limiting the intakes of animal
and high saturated fat foods
like meat and dairy.
Stricter adherence to the MIND diet
was associated with a 53% reduction
in risk for Alzheimer's disease.
In fact, even moderate adherence
appeared to cut risk by a third.
Overall, participants who showed
high adherence to the diet
had cognitive functioning equivalent
to a person who was 7.5 years younger.
No wonder people who ate meat,
including poultry and fish,
were more than twice as
likely to become demented
as their vegetarian counterparts,
and we're talking three times
the risk when past meat consumption
was taken into account.
This may be because plant-based
diets are known to preserve
body tissues from both
oxidative stress and inflammation,
hallmarks of these kinds
of degenerative diseases.
That may be why
berries are so protective,
since they're so rich in antioxidants,
and in terms of inflammation
those who avoid meat display
a higher abundance of
anti-inflammatory compounds
flowing through their systems
and lower levels of pro-inflammatory
indicators like C-reactive protein.
Dietary factors also influence the
effect of stress on cognitive decline.
Diets characterized by high intake
of animal proteins, saturated fats,
and added sugars, along with
low intakes of plant-based foods,
can increase secretion
of corticosteroids,
stress hormones like cortisol
from the adrenal glands,
which may promote the development
of Alzheimer's disease.
Then there are the gerontotoxins,
the aging toxins like AGEs,
advanced glycation end-products,
in our diet that may be a factor in
the development of Alzheimer's.
Safe foods, foods that contain
low AGE content, include starches
like whole grains, beans,
fruits, and vegetables,
whereas the worst sources
in the diet are broiled,
grilled, fried, or roasted meats.
The cooking process is important.
Chicken breast has an AGE content
of 1,000 units when boiled in water,
like chicken soup or something,
but that same chicken breast
jumps up to 9,000 when broiled.
Here s a list of the top 40
most AGE-contaminated foods
tested in terms of AGEs per serving.
As you can see it's almost all meat:
chicken, bacon, hot dogs,
and on down the list.
I tell people to choose raw
nuts and seeds to avoid AGEs,
but even roasted, toasted nuts
don't come close to making the list.
Now, of course, it's not just diet.
We need to get adequate sleep,
rest, and physical activity.
For example, daily brisk walks were
associated with a 40% lower risk
of developing Alzheimer's later in life,
and smoking may double your
risk of developing dementia.
But in terms of preventing
Alzheimer's with diet,
the key takeaways
are the following:
reduce added sugars,
saturated fat, animal products,
and processed foods in general,
while eating more plants,
especially greens and beans,
fruit, especially berries,
and reduce added salt.